# Frank Liu

I am a Ph.D. Student at Arizona State University, advised by Robert LiKamWa in the Meteor Studio. I am interested in enhancing human computer interaction experiences through mixed reality and machine learning, advancing education and encouraging overall health and wellness. I enjoy working on projects that incorporate my diverse skillset in signal processing, physical prototyping, machine learning and human-computer interaction.

PhD Candidate
Electrical, Computer &
Energy Engineering
Arizona State University
Tempe, AZ

Website

fwliu1.github.io

**Email** 

fwliu1@asu.edu

### **EDUCATION**

PhD Computer Engineering, Arizona State University

2018 - Present Advisor: Robert LiKamWa

BS Electrical Engineering – with Departmental Honors, University of Washington

2014 - 2018 Advisor: Hanchuan Li, Shwetak Patel

Summer 2020 Lean Six Sigma Green Belt

Summer 2016 University of California, Berkeley

Courses taken: Python and Big Data, Biostatistics

### SELECTED PEER-REVIEWED PUBLICATIONS

P4 Geppetteau: Enabling haptic perceptions of virtual fluids in various vessel profiles using a string-driven haptic interface

Shahabedin Sagheb\*, **Frank Wencheng Liu\***, Alex Vuong, Shiling Dai, Ryan Wirjadi, Yueming Bao, Robert Likamwa

TEI '23: Proceedings of the Seventeenth International Conference on Tangible, Embedded, and Embodied Interaction, Warsaw, Poland

P3 Spatial Audio Empowered Smart speakers with Xblock - A Pose-Adaptive Crosstalk Cancellation Algorithm for Free-moving Users

Frank Wencheng Liu\*, Anish Narsipur\*, Andrew Kemeklis, Lucy Song, Robert Likamwa CPS-IoT Week '23: 2nd ACM International Workshop on Intelligent Acoustic Systems and Applications, San Antonio, Texas

P2 SWISH: A shifting-weight interface of simulated hydrodynamics for haptic perception of virtual fluid vessels Shahabedin Sagheb, **Frank Wencheng Liu**, Alireza Bahremand, Assegid Kidane, Robert LiKamWa ACM UIST 2019, New Orleans, Louisiana

P1 SoberComm: Exploring the Feasibility of Facilitating Alcohol Dependent Patients to Improve Family Communication using Mobile Phones

Chuang-Wen You, Hung-Yeh Lin, Yaliang Chuang, Yi-Ching Huang, Jui-Ting Tsai, Shan Jean Wu, Chia-Hua Kuo, Ming-Chyi Huang, **Frank Wencheng Liu**, Jane Yung-Jen Hsu, Hui-Ching Wu.

ACM Interactive, Mobile, Wearable and Ubiquitous Technologies (IMWUT) September 2019

#### **HONORS & AWARDS**

Dean's Fellowship, Arizona State University

- Awarded to top 4% of admitted graduate students with significant leadership and research capabilities

Peter E. Crouch Excellence Fund, 2020-2021, Arizona State University

Ira A. Fulton Fellowship, 2019-2020, Arizona State University

Herbold Foundation Fellowship, 2019-2020, Arizona State University

Engineering Graduate Fellowship, 2019-2021, Arizona State University

Priscilla and Melvin Wilson Endowed Scholar, University of Washington

IEEE HKN Honors Society, University of Washington

- Scholastic achievement in the top 30% of graduating class

Husky Leadership Certificate, University of Washington

#### **WORKING EXPERIENCE**

Summer 2022 OPPO (InnoPeak Technology), Pal Alto, California

Research Intern

Worked on developing state-of-the-art gesture recognition for smartwatch applications

Summer 2020 Mochi Fresh, Tempe, Arizona

Independent Consultant

Utilizing DMAIC, I developed workflow optimizations to reduce restaurant variability and waste. Through

my contributions, Mochi Fresh nearly doubled revenue and halved drink making times.

Summer 2019 Clobotics, Bellevue, Washington

Computer Vision and Machine Learning Research Intern.

Shipped an end to end price tag decoding system for price and barcode reading for both android and GCP

Created and labeled US retail price tag dataset for training and testing.

Summer 2018 National Taiwan University - IoX Center, Gongguan, Taiwan

Research Intern. Mentor: Professor Bing You

Award of Excellence: Significant contributions in shipping android application SoberComm, allows alcohol

dependent individuals and their family members to monitor alcohol usage.

Spring 2018 Roxy Device, Seattle, Washington

Startup Intern.

Lead generation and public outreach for customer acquisition. Built, assembled, and QA tested Roxy Device

hardware systems.

Winter 2017 Microsoft, Redmond, Washington

Consultant.

Created labs, lessons and course content for the "Introduction to Device Programming" EDX (MICROSOFT COURSE) [DEV295X] using Microsoft's IOT Pack for Raspberry Pi for audience of thousand+ students.

#### RESEARCH FUNDING

Principal Investigator, 2023 ASU Changemaker Community Action Grant (Awarded)

Project Description: VR Club addresses the challenge of inadequately equipped classrooms and low-resource schools by pioneering virtual and augmented reality science labs. In underserved communities, where traditional lab equipment is scarce, this initiative harnesses augmented and virtual reality to provide immersive scientific experiences. Through these virtual labs, students can conduct experiments, visualize intricate concepts, and engage in interactive learning, all without physical apparatus limitations. This innovative solution not only overcomes resource constraints but also ensures equal access to quality education. We empower students to cocreate their own science educations, developing technology literacy and reinforcing science concepts. We envision educators using the experiences that the students have built in the classroom to empower other students learning.

Funding Amount: \$2,500

#### **PATENTS**

US 11,462,128 B2: Method and Apparatus for Simulated Hydrodynamics in Mixed – Reality Fluid Vessels Robert LiKamWa, Shahabedin Sagheb, Alireza Bahremand, Byron Lahey, Frank Wencheng Liu, Assegid Kidane

#### TEACHING EXPERIENCE

Arizona State Fall 2023: Teaching Assistant for AME 494: "Spatial Audio for XR" and AME 360 "Designing Mixed-Reality

University Experiences"

Fall 2022, Spring 2023: Co-Instructor for AME551, "Designing Extended-Reality Experiences"

Fall 2019: Teaching Assistant for AME 494, "Musical Microprocessors"

Spring 2019: Teaching Assistant for AME 394, "Introduction to Mixed Reality"

University of Fall 2016, Spring 2017, Spring 2018: Grader and Teaching Assistant for EE215,

Washington "Introduction to Circuits"

Coding with Kids Spring 2017, Classroom Instructor

Taught coding course curriculum for scratch at local Seattle elementary schools.

### **SERVICE**

Lead 2023, Led an interdisciplinary GenAl Student Committee at ASU, fostering discussions among PhD students

to address AI-related concerns and shape university policies, enhancing support for graduate research

involving AI tools like GenAI and ChatGPT.

Volunteer Hotmobile 2022, Poster and Demo Student Organizer

TEI 2019

Mentor Summer 2019, Advanced Robotics at the University of Washington

Summer 2019, Hacklodge Seattle

Member Fall 2017 – Spring 2018, The College of Engineering Student Advisory Council at University of Washington

Interviewed students and faculty about mental health on campus and prepared a recommendation report

# **INVITED TALKS**

December 2023	Exploring Generative AI in Education Through a Student Lens Speaker panel presented at Empowering Learnings in AI Conference
October 2023	VR Club $-$ Teaching VR in Highschools and Developing the Next Generation of Learners Presented for EdPlus at ASU
April 2023	A Stem Education You can Feel: Bringing Chemistry, Fluids, and Haptics into VR Learning Presented at Doctoral Academic Salon hosted by CCNU
April 2022	Digital Culture Speaker Series: A metaverse you can feel, building haptics for mixed reality
Scholar-Donor	From my exemplary leadership and service on campus, I was personally invited by Michael Bragg, Dean of the College of Engineering at UW, as a speaker for the 2017-2018 Scholar-Donor Recognition Luncheon.

## **LEADERSHIP**

TedXASU Organizing Team Spring 2019	Event with 1000+ tickets sold. Advised the development for the TedxASU application on android and iOS. Assisted in speaker selection, providing insights to the rest of the organizing team. Served in full capacity for event setup and takedown
Sunhacks Organizing Team Fall 2018	Lead marketing campaigns selling out tickets for 300+ participants Organized the largest hackathon in Phoenix Area; Sunhacks, ASU's 36-hour hackathon
Advanced Robotics at the University of Washington Spring 2017 – Summer 2018	Annotated meetings and weekly sprints coordinating 90 members Raised over 18,000 in funding through philanthropy efforts and sponsorships Refiller Robot Lead; Designed and conducted CAD reviews; wrote embedded software (C, C++, Arduino) for robot control systems Summer 2018 Placed 3rd in International Regionals  Summer 2017 Placed 31st out of 241 at International DJI Robomasters competition in Shenzhen, China

# **REFERENCES**

Robert LiKamWa	likamwa@asu.edu
NUDELL LINGILIVA	iikaiiiwai∞asu.∈uu

Mina Johnson-

Glenberg

Mina. Johnson@asu.edu

Shwetak Patel shwetak@cs.washington.edu